Elizabeth Morrow Personal Papers, 1892-1947
Smith College Archives
Elizabeth Morrow Personal Papers
1892-1947
Morrow, Elizabeth, 1873-1955.
RG 32 UUID:3ccef6af-899e-4ce3-90da-88d69caea8ce
5 boxes (1.9 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
The Elizabeth Morrow personal papers contain biographical material, correspondence, memorials, photographs, publications, and speeches, as well as an unpublished book of verse produced as a tribute for Morrow.
Elizabeth Reeve Cutter Morrow has been called Smith's most outstanding alumna. Born in Cleveland, Ohio in 1873, Elizabeth Cutter was the daughter of Charles Long Cutter and Annie E. (Spencer) Cutter. Her father was Secretary General of L. and Wheeling Railroad. Having received her early education at Miss Mittleberger's School in Cleveland, she was later granted a B. L. degree from Smith College in the Class of 1896. She studied at the Sorbonne in Paris, France from 1896 to 1897 as well as in Florence, Italy.
In 1903 she married Dwight Whitney Morrow. Dwight Morrow, born in Huntington, West Virginia in 1873, graduated from Amherst College in 1896. He served as the United States Ambassador to Mexico from 1927-1930, during the Hoover administration, and served in the United States Senate between 1930 until his death on October 5, 1931. They had four children: Elizabeth Reeve Morrow (Class of 1923), Anne Spencer Morrow (Class of 1928), Dwight Whitney Morrow Jr., and Constance Cutter Morrow (Class of 1935). Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was the grandmother of twelve, including Charles Augustus Lindbergh, Jr. the famous Lindbergh baby, son of Anne Spencer Morrow and her husband Col. Charles A. Lindbergh.
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was the recipient of honorary degrees from six leading colleges and universities including: Amherst College, 1933; New Jersey College for Women, 1935; Smith College, 1937; New York University, 1940; Lafayette College, 1940; and Princeton, 1940. Described by Dr. William Allen Neilson in conferring the degree of Doctor of Humane letters upon her in 1937, "President of the Alumnae Association, and for sixteen years Trustee of Smith College, author of distinction in prose and verse, the multitude of whose services to her college and her country - far greater than the world knows - makes it impossible to describe adequately the alumna who has earned in most abundant measure our love, our honor, and our gratitude."
Taking an active role in the life and well-being of her alma mater, Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was president of the Smith College Alumnae Association from 1917-1920. She was a member of the War Services Board which directed Smith College relief units overseas. Between 1920-1926 she was the Alumnae representative to the Board of Trustees, and later, in 1926, was elected a Trustee by the Board. Her largest contribution, however, was her role as acting president for the interim year, 1939-1940, after the resignation of William A. Neilson as president in 1939.
Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was not a professional woman whose "field" can be easily described. She certainly achieved eminence in education, philanthropy, finance, and literature. She was a teacher of English, History, and French in private schools before her marriage to Dwight Whitney Morrow in 1903. During her marriage she published prose and verse in many popular magazines, as well as publishing multiple children's books, of which some are The Painted Pig, Quatrains for My Daughter, The Rabbit's Nest, Shannon, A Pint of Judgment, and Casa Manana which was chosen as one of 150 of the most beautiful books between 1931 and 1933.
Her volunteer work had no limits. Elizabeth Cutter Morrow was unstintingly active in local as well as national and international affairs. She was chairman of the Community Chest when it was first organized in Englewood, New Jersey, the town she called home. She was also involved in her local church, Women's Club, Memorial House (civic center) and was even chairman of the Board of The Little School in Englewood, founded by her daughter Elizabeth. She was a member of the Executive Committee of the New York National War Fund Committee. She was one of the founders for Food for Freedom Inc.. She was the first woman to serve on the Board of the Union Theological Seminary. In New York she was a member of the National Board of the Y. W. C. A., and she took a leading role in many of its campaigns for funds. Elizabeth Cutter Morrow played an important role in issues abroad. During her husband's time as Ambassador to Mexico, 1927-30, she supported him in his resolve to bring about the strengthening of friendly relations between Mexico and the United States. As well, she was an honorary vice-president of the American Association for the United Nations, Inc.
On January 23, 1955 she died at the age of eighty-two. In an address at the Smith College memorial service Ada Comstock Notestein, member of the Class of 1897, former Dean and Trustee of Smith College, as well as former president of Radcliffe College, said: "…She was one of those rare beings for whose courage nothing is too great, and for whose imagination nothing is too small….She was a benefactor and philanthropist without any apparent consciousness of doing more than anyone would have done in her place."
The Elizabeth Morrow papers document Morrow's life outside of her presidency at Smith. Types of material include biographical material, newspaper clippings, correspondence, memorials, photographs, publications, and speeches. The bulk of the collection consists of photographs and publications.
This collection is organized into four series:
Series I. Biographical Materials
Series II. Photographs
Series III. Publications
Series IV. Speeches
The records are open for research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives without any additional restrictions.
The Elizabeth Morrow papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Office of the Acting President Elizabeth Morrow Files, 1939-1940
- Series I. Biographical Materials
  - General 1948-1956, undated (Box 445, Folder 1)
  - Clippings 1930-1949, 1982, undated (Box 445, Folder 2)
  - Citations 1947 (Box 445, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence 1939, undated (Box 445, Folder 4)
  - Cutter, Annie Spencer 1957 (Box 445, Folder 5)
  - Honorary degrees 1933-1940 (Box 445, Folder 6)
  - General undated (Box 445, Folder 7)
  - Memorial services and obituary 1955 (Box 445, Folder 8)
  - Memorials and tributes 1955-1958, undated (Box 445, Folder 9)
  - Morrow, Dwight Whitney 1922-1951, undated (Box 445, Folder 10)
  - Phi Beta Kappa undated (Box 445, Folder 11)
- Series II. Photographs
  - Undergraduate (Box 445, Folder 12)
  - Undergraduate: individual and with Kate Williams (Box 445, Folder 13)
  - Undergraduate: room in Hubbard House (Box 445, Folder 14)
  - Undergraduate: with friends ca. 1896 (Box 445, Folder 15)
  - Personal and family undated (Box 445, Folder 16)
  - High school graduation 1892 (Box 445, Folder 17)
  - Amherst Junior Prom 1895 (Box 445, Folder 18)
  - Alumnae parade 1931 (Box 445, Folder 19)
  - Mexico 1934 (Box 445, Folder 20)
  - Honorary degrees 1937, 1948 (Box 445, Folder 21)
  - Acting President of Smith College 1940 (Box 445, Folder 22)
  - Bust 1940 (Box 445, Folder 23)
  - Sitting on bench 1940 (Box 445, Folder 24)
  - Inaugural of the Women's Division of Fight for Freedom 1941, 1944 (Box 445, Folder 25)
  - 75th Anniversary Fund 1949-1950 (Box 445, Folder 26)
  - Cleveland 1950 (Box 445, Folder 27)
  - Portraits 1941-1953, undated (Box 445, Folder 28)
- Series III. Publications
  - Publications 1940-1947, undated (Box 446, Folder 1)
  - "A Defense of College Women" 1933 (Box 446, Folder 2)
  - A Pint of Judgment 1939 (Box 446, Folder 3)
  - "An Old Map" 1951 (Box 446, Folder 4)
  - "Our Street in Cuernavaca" 1931 (Box 446, Folder 5)
  - Quatrains for My Daughter 1928 (Box 446, Folder 6)
  - The Rabbit's Nest 1940 (Box 446, Folder 7)
  - Shannon 1941 (Box 446, Folder 8)
  - Sonnet 1937 (Box 446, Folder 9)
  - William Allen Neilson blueprint for biography 1947 (Box 446, Folder 10)
  - Youth Replies, I Can (Foreword) 1945 (Box 446, Folder 11)
- Series IV. Speeches
  - Speeches 1939-1947, undated (Box 446, Folder 12)
  - Alumnae Association 1920-1940 (Box 446, Folder 13)
  - Alumnae Council 1940 (Box 446, Folder 14)
  - Assembly 1932-1946, undated (Box 446, Folder 15)
  - Chapel talks 1939-1940 (Box 446, Folder 16)
  - "College Women and the New Leisure" 1934, undated (Box 446, Folder 17)
  - "Does America Deserve a Miracle" 1940 (Box 446, Folder 18)
  - Inauguration of President Benjamin F. Wright undated (Box 446, Folder 19)
  - Seven colleges 1931 (Box 446, Folder 20)
  - Tributes: handmade book of verse 1940 (Box 446, Folder 21)